Finding aid for the L.A. Youth newspapers and records, 1989-2013 LSC.2297
UCLA Library Special Collections
L.A. Youth newspapers and records
1989-2013
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2297
4.2 Linear Feet (1 box, 7 flat boxes, 5 CD boxes)
This collection documents the publications, copyright agreements, digital archives, and release forms of the independent student-written publication L.A. Youth, which ran from 1989 to 2013. It was the largest teen-run newspaper in the United States, and became known for tackling controversial topics like gang violence, mental illness, teen homelessness, and partner abuse.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Youth News Service, dba L.A. Youth, 2015.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9979898633606533
Biography/History
L.A. Youth was an independent, city-wide, teen-written newspaper that ran for 25 years, from 1988 to 2013. It was created by former teacher Donna Myrow in response to the U.S. Supreme Court decision in Hazelwood School District v. Kuhlmeier, which empowered school administrators to control the content of school publications.
By 2002, L.A. Youth had an estimated readership of 350,000, making it the largest teen independent newspaper in the United States. The newspaper, published every two months, was distributed for free to teachers in public, private, and charter schools, community-based youth programs, and libraries, as well as centers for juvenile justice and foster care. The paper was also sent abroad to students in China, France, and Africa.
In 2003, L.A. Youth's Foster Youth Writing and Education Project expanded its staff of writers to youth in foster care and probation systems. As a tax-exempt non-profit, L.A. Youth partnered with organizations to fund their magazine and promote awareness on issues like destigmatizing mental illness and advocating green living. Issues tackled subjects as wide-ranging as homelessness, gang violence, suicide, sex education, electoral politics, educational reform, immigration, and homophobia.
From 2002-2005, eight L.A. Youth students were recognized at the Los Angeles Times High School Journalism Awards, and L.A. Youth stories were reprinted in the Los Angeles Times (who provided major funding for printing costs) and The New York Times, as well as adapted for NPR. Alums went on to work at the Baltimore Sun, the Boston Globe, the Los Angeles Times, NPR, Newsweek, and the Chicago Reporter, among other top publications.
California's financial crisis and the 2008 recession hurt L.A. Youth's funding, and the newspaper closed shortly after publishing its 25th anniversary issue. Their sister publication in New York, Represent Magazine, is still running.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the writings of the independent student-written publication L.A. Youth, which ran for 25 years before closing operations in 2013. By 2002, it had an estimated readership of 350,000, distributed for free to teachers in public, private, and charter schools, community-based youth programs, and libraries, as well as centers for juvenile justice and foster care. In addition to print issues and a digital archive, the collection contains a guide to student journalism, copyright forms, and release form by writers' parents and juvenile courts.
Materials are largely textual, comprising print issues of the publication and copyright and court release forms. Among other formats are CDs and DVDs.
Some significant topics represented in these files are: gun violence, poverty, homelessness, mental illness, religious intolerance, immigration, racism, police brutality, homophobia, domestic abuse and partner violence, sexual assault, gang warfare, addiction, the foster care system, school shootings, weight issues, self-harm, school censorship, environmental activism, affirmative action, and student employment.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Print Issues (1989-2013)
Series 2: Digital Archives and Production Files (1996-2013)
Series 3: Copyright and Release Agreements (1998-2013)
The collection's series have been organized by publication date or subject name.
Student newspapers and periodicals
- Print Issues, 1989-2013
  Scope and Content
  This series comprises copies of the paper issues published every two months by L.A. Youth from 1989 to 2013. Significant topics include gun violence, poverty, homelessness, mental illness, religious intolerance, immigration, racism, police brutality, homophobia, domestic abuse and partner violence, sexual assault, gang warfare, addiction, the foster care system, school shootings, weight issues, self-harm, school censorship, environmental activism, affirmative action, student employment, and the LA art scene.
  Organization and Arrangement
  This series has been organized chronologically.
  - Feb - June, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Feb - July, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - April - October, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - April - July, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sept - Dec, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - March - Dec, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Nov - Feb, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - May - Feb, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - March - May, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - May - Oct, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Nov - Feb, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - March - June, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sept - Dec, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jan - April, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - May - Oct, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nov - Dec, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jan - April, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - May - Oct, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Nov - Dec, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jan - April, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - May - Oct, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nov - Dec, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jan - April, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - May - Oct, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Nov - Dec, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jan - June, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sept - Oct, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nov - Feb, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - March - June, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sept - Dec, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Jan - April, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - May - Sept, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oct - Nov, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Jan - April, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - May - Sept, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Oct - Nov, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Jan - April, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - May - Sept, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Oct - Dec, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Jan - April, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - May - Sept, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Oct - Dec, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Jan - April, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - May - Sept, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Oct - Dec, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Jan - April, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - May - Sept, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Oct - Dec, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Jan - April, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - May - Sept, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Oct - Dec, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Jan - June, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sept - Oct, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Jan - April, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Death by Cheeseburger: High School Journalism in the 1990s and Beyond (The Freedom Forum), 1994 (Box 7)
    Book on the history of high school journalism published by Freedom Forum in 1994.
- Digital Archives and Production Files, 1996-2013
  This series comprises digital records of the artwork and articles published by L.A. Youth from 1996 to 2013, as well as advertisements, image files, teachers' guides, and other web materials. Significant topics include gun violence, poverty, homelessness, mental illness, religious intolerance, immigration, racism, police brutality, homophobia, domestic abuse and partner violence, sexual assault, gang warfare, addiction, the foster care system, school shootings, weight issues, self-harm, school censorship, environmental activism, affirmative action, student employment, and the LA art scene.
  Series contains 239 CDs (digital issues), 45 DVDs (designs, photos, ads).
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 1996 (Box 10)
  - March - April (1-2), 1996 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-2), 1996 (Box 10)
  - Sept - Oct (1-2), 1996 (Box 10)
  - Nov - Dec (1-4), 1996 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 1997 (Box 10)
  - Mar - April (1-2), 1997 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-3), 1997 (Box 10)
  - Sept - Oct (1-2), 1997 (Box 10)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 1997 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 1998 (Box 10)
  - March - April (1-2), 1998 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-2), 1998 (Box 10)
  - Sept - Oct (1-2), 1998 (Box 10)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 1998 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - March - April (1-2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - Sept - Oct (1-2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 2000 (Box 10)
  - March - April (1-2), 2000 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-2), 2000 (Box 10)
  - August, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Fall (1-2), 2000 (Box 10)
  - Sept - Oct (1-3), 2000 (Box 10)
  - Nov (1-2), 2000 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-4), 2001 (Box 10)
  - March - April (1-4), 2001 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-5), 2001 (Box 10)
  - Sept - Oct (1-4), 2001 (Box 10)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 2001 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-6), 2002 (Box 10)
  - March - April (1-4), 2002 (Box 10)
  - May - June (1-4), 2002 (Box 10)
  - Sept- Oct (1-2), 2002 (Box 10)
  - Sports Fall (1-3), 2002 (Box 10)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 2002 (Box 10)
  - Jan - Feb (1-5), 2003 (Box 10, Box 11)
  - March - April (1-6), 2003 (Box 11)
  - May - June (1-4), 2003 (Box 11)
  - Fall Jobs (1-4), 2003 (Box 11)
  - Sept (1-4), 2003 (Box 11)
  - Nov - Dec (1-4), 2003 (Box 11)
  - Jan (1-5), 2004 (Box 11)
  - March - April (1-4), 2004 (Box 11)
  - May - June (1-4), 2004 (Box 11)
  - Sept (1-4), 2004 (Box 11)
  - Oct (1-4), 2004 (Box 11)
  - Nov - Dec (1-4), 2004 (Box 11)
  - LA Youth Beta Tape, 2005-2007 (Box 13)
  - Jan - Feb (1-5), 2005 (Box 13)
  - March - April (1-6), 2005 (Box 13)
  - May - June (1-4) (Box 13)
  - Sept (1-4), 2005 (Box 13)
  - Oct (1-4), 2005 (Box 13)
  - Nov (1-2), 2005 (Box 13)
  - Jan - Feb (1-4), 2006 (Box 13)
  - March - April (1-4), 2006 (Box 13)
  - May - June (1-4), 2006 (Box 13)
  - Sept (1-4), 2006 (Box 13)
  - Oct (1-4), 2006 (Box 13)
  - Nov (1-4), 2006 (Box 13)
  - Jan - Feb (1-4), 2007 (Box 13)
  - March - April (1-6), 2007 (Box 12)
  - May (1-6), 2007 (Box 12)
  - Sept (1-6), 2007 (Box 12)
  - Oct (1-3), 2007 (Box 12)
  - Nov (1-3), 2007 (Box 12)
  - Jan (1-10), 2008 (Box 12)
  - March (1-2), 2008 (Box 12)
  - May - June (1-2), 2008 (Box 12)
  - Sept (1-2), 2008 (Box 12)
  - Oct (1-2), 2008 (Box 12)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 2008 (Box 12)
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 2009 (Box 12)
  - March - April, 2009 (Box 12)
  - May - June (1-2), 2009 (Box 12)
  - Sept (1-4), 2009 (Box 12)
  - Oct (1-3), 2009 (Box 12)
  - Nov - Dec, 2009 (Box 12)
  - Jan - Feb (1-2), 2010 (Box 12)
  - March - April, 2010 (Box 12)
  - May - June, 2010 (Box 12)
  - Sept (1-2), 2010 (Box 9)
  - Oct (1-3), 2010 (Box 9)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 2010 (Box 9)
  - Jan - Feb, 2011 (Box 9)
  - March - April, 2011 (Box 9)
  - May - June, 2011 (Box 9)
  - Sept, 2011 (Box 9)
  - Oct, 2011 (Box 9)
  - Nov - Dec, 2011 (Box 9)
  - Jan - Feb, 2012 (Box 9)
  - March - April (1-2), 2012 (Box 9)
  - May - June (1-2), 2012 (Box 9)
  - Sept (1-3), 2012 (Box 9)
  - Oct (1-2), 2012 (Box 9)
  - Nov - Dec (1-2), 2012 (Box 9)
  - Jan - Feb (1-5), 2013 (Box 9)
  - Foster Youth EPS (Jan), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Fonts (March), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Education Report (March), 2001 (Box 9)
  - CTI Reports (May), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Dinner Programs (May), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Anniversary Campaign (Sept), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Ads (Oct), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Invites (Nov), 2001 (Box 9)
  - Moritz Design (Jan), 2002 (Box 9)
  - Newsletters (Jan), 2002 (Box 9)
  - Youth Chronicles (May), 2002 (Box 9)
  - Website Postcard (March), 2002 (Box 9)
  - Get Real Campaign (May), 2002 (Box 9)
- Copyright and Release Agreements, 1998-2013
  This series comprises copyright forms allowing L.A. Youth to publish teen writers' works and confirm that they will be credited as authors, as well as releases from parents and juvenile court, including the Foster Youth Court, to allow interviewing, photographing, videotaping, and publishing works by minors. This series spans 1989 to 2013.
  This series has been organized by last name.
  - Copyright: A-B, 1998-2013 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Copyright: C-D, 1998-2013 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Copyright: E-H, 1998-2012 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Copyright: I-K, 1999-2012 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Copyright: L-O, 1998-2013 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Copyright: S-R, 1998-2013 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Copyright: V-Z, 1997-2013 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Releases: A-G, 2005-2013 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Releases: H-P, 2004-2009 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Releases: R-Z, 2006-2011 (Box 8, Folder 10)